Guide to the Warren Bartlett Seabury Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Warren Bartlett Seabury papers
1901-1936
MS 790
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
(2 boxes)
Correspondence, essays and memorabilia of Warren Bartlett Seabury, a missionary in China who helped plan and organize the Yale Foreign Missionary Society. Correspondence with his family (1904-1907) and reports on his work for the Society and the founding of the Yali Middle School are included. Among his correspondents are Harlan Page Beach, Edward Bliss Reed. John P. Rice and Arthur C. Williams.
Seabury, Warren Bartlett, 1877-1907
Arrangement
Arranged in five series: I. Family Correspondence. II. General Correspondence. III. Correspondence of Joseph Bartlett Seabury. IV. Writings. V. Miscellany.
Scope and Contents
The Warren Bartlett Seabury Papers are divided into five series: I. Family Correspondence; II. General Correspondence; III. Correspondence of Joseph Bartlett Seabury; IV. Writings; and V. Miscellany.
Series I, FAMILY CORRESPONDENCE, contains the letters written by Seabury to his family during 1904-1907, the period in which he was in China. The letters are weekly summaries of Seabury's work for the Yale Foreign Missionary Society and contain comments on his reactions to the Chinese people and culture. Subjects discussed at length include Seabury's efforts to purchase land for the Yale Mission and the founding of what was to become Yali Middle School. A single earlier letter, dated November, 1901, relates to Seabury's role in the founding and organization of the Yale Foreign Missionary Society.
Series II, GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE, contains letters between Seabury and members of the Yale Foreign Missionary Society staff. Correspondents of note include: Harlan Page Beach, 1903-1907; Edward Bliss Reed, 1903-1907; John P. Rice, 1904-1906; Arthur C. Williams, 1901-1905.
Series III, CORRESPONDENCE OF JOSEPH B. SEABURY, contains letters between Warren Seabury's father and Yale Foreign Missionary Society staff members discussing Seabury's death and the establishment of a memorial fund.
Series IV, WRITINGS, contains twenty-five short essays and sketches written by Seabury between 1904-1907 on various aspects of his life in China. Also included is a copy of a class oration written at the Hartford Theological Seminary in 1903.
Series V, MISCELLANY, contains copies of Seabury's obituaries and memorials, several student essays corrected by Seabury, a draft copy of rules and regulations of the Yale Mission College edited in Seabury's hand, and a portrait of Seabury.
Biographical / Historical
Warren Bartlett Seabury, the son of Joseph Bartlett and Martha Daniels Seabury, was born in Lowell, Massachusetts, on September 17, 1877. After preparing for college at Hotchkiss, he entered Yale College as a member of the class of 1900. After graduation from Yale, Seabury enrolled at the Hartford Theological Seminary and received the B.D. degree in 1903. The following year was spent studying comparative religion at the Yale Graduate School where he received his M.A. in 1904.
While a student at the Hartford Theological Seminary, Seabury helped plan and organize the Yale Foreign Missionary Society, and after being ordained as a minister in 1904, he sailed for China to help organize the Yale Mission's educational work.
Seabury's first two years in China were spent studying Chinese in Hankow and negotiating the purchase of a mission site in Changsha. By November, 1906, he had succeeded in establishing the middle school in temporary quarters and begun teaching.
On July 29, 1907, while on a holiday vacation near Kuling, Seabury drowned in a swimming accident. For further information see the biography of Seabury, The Vision of a Short Life, by his father Joseph Bartlett Seabury (Cambridge, 1908).
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Missions -- China; Asia; China -- Social life and customs; Clergy; Missionaries; Beach, Harlan P. (Harlan Page), 1854-1933; Reed, Edward Bliss, 1872-1940; Rice, John Pierrepont; Seabury, Warren Bartlett, 1877-1907; Williams, Arthur Collins, 1876-1917; Yale University -- Officals and employees; Yale-China Association; Yali Middle School
- FAMILY CORRESPONDENCE, 1901-1907; Series I; .25 linear feet (6 folders)
  Scope and Contents
  FAMILY CORRESPONDENCE is arranged chronologically.
  - 1901, 1904, 1905 January - May, 1905 June - Dec, 1906, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
- GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE, 1901-1907; Series II; .25 linear feet (13 folders)
  GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Letters of a particular correspondent are arranged chronologically.
  - Beach, Harlan Page, 1903-1907 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Eddy, E. Brewer, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Reed, Edward Bliss, 1903-1907 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Rice, John P., 1904-1906 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Sanders, Frank Knight, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Stokes, Anson Phelps, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Thurston, J. Lawrence, 1902-1903 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Williams, Arthur C., 1901-1905 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Williams, F. Wells, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Wright, Henry B., 1905 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Yale Foreign Missionary Society, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- CORRESPONDENCE OF JOSEPH BARTLETT SEABURY, 1903-1914; Series III; .25 linear feet (2 folders)
  CORRESPONDENCE OF JOSEPH BARTLETT SEABURY is arranged chronologically.
  - 1903-1914 (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
- WRITINGS, 1903-1907; Series IV; .25 linear feet (5 folders)
  WRITINGS are arranged alphabetically by title.
  - "Call Upon the Governor and the Banquet" (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - "Character of the Chinese" (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - "Chinese Customs" (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - "Chinese Streets" (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - "Class Oration, 1903" (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - "Cold and Heat in China" (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - "The Convert Zau" (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - "Deception as Practiced by the Chinese" (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - "The Dress of the Chinese" (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - "Drops Out of the Bucket of My Experience" (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - "English as She Is Spoke and Written in China" (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "Dr. Griffith John" (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "Life in China" (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "Night and Early Dawn" (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "One Type of Missionary" (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "Peking" (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "A Short Journey Through the Heart of Hunan" (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - "The Sing Song Cure" (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - "The Soul" (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - "Stray Leaves" (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - "A Summer Night in a Chinese Harbor" (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - "Teaching English" (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - "To Keep Himself Unspotted from the World" (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - "Visit to a Sacred Place" (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - "The Yale University Mission in China" (Box 2, Folder 26)
- MISCELLANY, 1904-1936; Series V; .25 linear feet (3 folders)
  The materials in MISCELLANY are grouped together according to form.
  - Student essays (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - "Rules and Regulations of Yale Mission College" draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Obituary notices and memorials Photograph: Warren Bartlett Seabury (Box 2, Folder 29)